Guide to the New York agricultural leaders oral history project, 1962-1968.
New York agricultural leaders oral history project
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
New York agricultural leaders oral history project, 1962-1968.
13-6-428
Cornell University. Program in Oral History.
60 volumes.
Transcripts of interviews.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes interviews with farmers, officials of the State Grange, New York State and American Farm Bureau Federations, the Dairymen's League, GLF, and other agricultural businesses, county agents, extension specialists, faculty and staff members of the New York State College of Agriculture, and others involved in agriculture in New York State.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes interviews with farmers, officials of the State Grange, New York State and American Farm Bureau Federations, the Dairymen's League, GLF, and other agricultural businesses, county agents, extension specialists, faculty and staff members of the New York State College of Agriculture, and others involved in agriculture in New York State.
Subjects discussed include student days in the College of Agriculture; production and marketing of beef poultry, dairy products, and apples and other orchard fruit; farm practice and management, including the use of cost accounting, access to credit, and procurement and management of labor; experiences in organizing farmers, particularly in fruit-marketing cooperatives; relationship of farmers to the Extension Service and Farm Bureau, impressions of early county agents, and farmers' reactions to tuberculosis and brucellosis control; formation of the American Farm Bureau Federation, activities of both the American and State Farm Bureaus, including the relationship between the two, decision making in the latter, and separation of the Farm Bureau from the State Extension Service; founding of the Dairymen's League, sources of support and opposition, decision making in the organization, milk control legislation, milk marketing, changing of the League from a bargaining to an operating organization, and its relationship to other milk-marketing organizations; formation of the Grange League Federation (GLF), raising its capital funds, decision making, research, development of retail and supply services, information and public relations, marketing activities, credit policies, establishing its insurance company, expansion of territory, and relationship to agricultural colleges, farm organizations, and competitors; the work of county agents and their association with the College staff, other agents, and county agricultural organizations; teaching, research, and extension work at the College of Agriculture, in agricultural economics, agricultural engineering, agronomy, animal husbandry, bacteriology, biochemistry, botany, conservation, entomology, farm practice, pomology, and vegetable crops; activities of Edward H. Thomson as president of the Federal Land Bank of Springfield, Mass.; Albert B. Genung's work in the Bureau of Agricultural Economics, USDA; George F. Warren's career, as recalled by his associates; Rockefeller Foundation-sponsored programs for crop improvement (1940-1962) in Mexico, Colombia, and the Far East; Halsey B. Knapp's experiences as director of the Long Island Agricultural and Technical Institute in Farmingdale and as leader of the Cornell-Los Banos Project at the University of the Philippines; and the characteristics of the seed business in New York State.
References are made to the organization or activities of the Conference Board of Farm Organizations, Dairy Farmers of America, Dairy Record Club, Empire Livestock Marketing Cooperative, Holstein-Friesian Association, National Poultry Industry Planning Committee, New York State Fruit Testing Association, New York State Horticultural Society, New York State Poultry Council, N.Y.S. School of Agriculture at Cobleskill, Northeastern Poultry Products Council, USDA Office of Farm Management, Pharsalia Project, Poultry and Egg National Board, Producers Cooperative Commission Association of Buffalo, Rochester Production Credit Association, Rural Radio Network, Soil Conservation Service, and Western New York Apple Growers Association.
There are also recollections of or references to Bristow Adams, G. F. Atkinson, H. E. Babcock, William Barrett, Liberty Hyde Bailey, Earl W. Benjamin, Maurice C. Burritt, Anna Botsford and John Henry Comstock, N. J. Cladakis, Lane Cooper, Edmund Ezra Day, Thomas E. Dewey, R. A. Emerson, Edmund H. Fallon, Livingston Farrand, Verne A. Fogg, Edward S. Foster, Fred Freestone, Beverly T. Galloway, Frank E. Gannett, Cedric Guise, Albert Hoefer, Ralph S. Hosmer, Lewis Knudson, Carl E. Ladd, Fiorello LaGuardia, K. C. Livermore, Albert R. Mann, James McConnell, Thomas E. Milliman, William I. Myers, James G. Needham, A. B. Recknagel, James E. Rice, William A. Riley, Isaac P. Roberts, Flora Rose, Willard W. Rowlee, Elmer S. Savage, Fred Sexauer, Earl Smith, Mark V. Slingerland, Leland Spencer, Samuel Spring, H. H. Whetzel, K. M. Wiegand, Burt Green Wilder, H. H. Wing, George A. Works, E. L. Worthen, Archie Wright, Martha Van Rensselaer, and Owen D. Young.
There are interviews with Albert Blanchard, William Barrett, Ray Bender, Frank W. Beneway, Earl W. Benjamin, Albert Blanchard, Bartow W. Bull, Walter Clickman, William L. Colton, James C. Corwith, Harold Cowles, Verne A. Fogg, Edward S. Foster, Bruce Gervan, Donald F. Green, Sr., Herbert B. Hartwig, Warren W. Hawley, Jr., Raymond C. Hitchings, John C. Huttar, George Lamb, Thomas E. LaMont, James McConnell, Elizabeth MacDonald, Thomas E. Milliman, Harlan B. Munger, Horace W. Norton, Edgar Raish, Seymour K. Rodenhurst, Orrin F. Ross, Fred D. Rumsey, Clarence M. Slack, Paul Smith, William S. Secord, Jared W. Stiles, Harold M. Stanley, Clayton C. Taylor, Edward H. Thomson, E. Victor Underwood, Reverdy and William P. Wadsworth, William Waldorf, and Carl Warren. Also, Cornell professors Richard Bradfield, Chester J. Bradley, Arthur J. Eames, Albert B. Genung, Anson W. Gibson, Van B. Hart, Herbert B. Hartwig, Glenn W. Hedlund, Glenn W. Herrick, Burton A. Jennings, Asa King, Halsey B. Knapp, Laurence H. MacDaniels, L. A. Maynard, Benton S. Monroe, William I. Myers, E. Laurence Palmer, Howard W. Riley, Gad P. Scoville, S. Reuben Shapley, Lloyd R. Simons, George W. Tailby, Homer C. Thompson, Edmund L. Worthen, Albert H. and Anna A. Wright, and Bailey Hortorium Curator Ethel Zoe Bailey.
Also, interviews with William H. Chandler, who taught pomology at Cornell from 1913 to 1923, conducted by Elizabeth I. Dixon, Librarian of the Oral History Program at UCLA, at the request of Gould P. Colman in early 1963. Transcript is dated 1965.
Most of the interviews were conducted by Gould P. Colman. Other interviewers include graduate students J. Warren Adair, Richard H. Bliss, Jonathan Levine, and Ethan Windahl.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Cornell University.; Adams, Bristow, 1875-1957.; Atkinson, George Francis, 1854-1918.; Babcock, H. E. (Howard Edward), 1889-1950.; Bailey, Ethel Zoe.; Bailey, L. H. (Liberty Hyde), 1858-1954.; Barrett, William, 1888-1978.; Bender, Ray, 1905-1975.; Beneway, Frank W., 1884-1994.; Benjamin, Earl Whitney, 1889-1972.; Bradfield, Richard, 1896-1981.; Bradley, J. Chester (James Chester), 1884-1975.; Bull, Bartow B., 1874-1965.; Burritt, M. C. (Maurice Chase); Carey, Daniel, 1897-1976.; Chandler, William Henry, 1878-1970.; Colman, Gould P. (Gould Patchin), 1926- ,; Comstock, Anna Botsford, 1854-1930.; Comstock, John Henry, 1849-1931.; Cooper, Lane, 1875-1959.; Cowles, Harold.; Day, Edmund Ezra, 1883-1951.; Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971.; Dixon, Elizabeth I.,; Eames, Arthur J., 1881-1969.; Emerson, Rollins Adams, 1873-1947.; Falllon, Edmund D.; Farrand, Livingston, 1867-1939.; Fogg, Verne A., 1897-1987.; Foster, Edward Shields, 1901-1973.; Freestone, Fred.; Galloway, Beverly T., 1863-1938,; Gannett, Frank E. (Frank Ernest), 1876-1957.; Genung, Albert Benjamin, 1890-1963.; Gervan, R. Bruce, 1907-1993.; Gibson, Anson Wright, 1892-1977.; Green, Donald, 1903-1989.; Guise, Cedric H. (Cedric Hay), 1890-; Hart, Van Breed, 1894-1976.; Hawley, Warren Waldo, Jr., 1891-1982.; Herrick, Glenn W. (Glenn Washington), 1870-1965.; Hoefer, Albert.; Hosmer, Ralph S. (Ralph Sheldon), 1874-1963.; Huttar, John C., 1902-1988.; Jennings, Burton Aaron, 1895-1964.; King, Asa Carlton, 1877-1967.; Knapp, Halsey, 1888-1976.; Knudson, Lewis, 1884-1958.; Ladd, Carl E. (Carl Edwin), 1888-1943.; LaGuardia, Fiorello H. (Fiorello Henry), 1882-1947.; LaMont, Thomas E., 1906-1970.; Levine, Jonathan.,; Livermore, K. C., (Kenneth Carter), 1886-; Mann, Albert Russell, 1880-1947.; Maynard, L. A. (Leonard Amby), 1887-1972.; McConnell, James, 1891-1974.; Milliman, Thomas E., 1890-1971.; Monroe, Benton Sullivan, 1873-1968.; Munger, Harlan B., 1888-1969.; Myers, William Irving, 1891-1976.; Needham, James G. (James George), 1868-1957.; Norton, Horace A., 1883-1971.; Palmer, E. Laurence (Ephraim Laurence), 1888-1970.; Recknagle, A. B. (Arthur Bernhard), 1883-1962.; Rice, James E. (James Edward), 1865-1953.; Riley, Howard W., 1879-1971.; Riley, William A. (William Albert), 1876-; Roberts, Isaac Phillips, 1883-1928.; Rodenhurst, Seymour K. 1893-1973.; Rowlee, Willard Winfield, 1861-; Savage, Elmer Seth, 1884-; Shapley, S. Reuben, 1906-1997.; Simons, L. R.; Slack, Clarence M., 1894-1976.; Slingerland, M. V. (Mark Vernon), 1864-1909.; Smith, Earl.; Smith, Paul, 1889-; Spencer, Leland, 1896-; Spring, Samuel N. (Samuel Newton), 1875-1952.; Stempfle, William Secord, 1895-1982.; Stiles, Jared W., 1907-1974.; Tailby, George W., 1882-1965.; Taylor, Clayton Charles, Jr., 1898-1979.; Thompson, Homer C., 1885-1976.; Thomson, Edward Herrmann, 1887-1967.; Underwood, E. Victor, 1889-1974.; Wadsworth, Reverdy J., 1914-1970.; Wadsworth, William P., 1906-1982.; Wakely, Philip C., 1902-1983.; Waldorf, William E., 1916-2000.; Warren, Carl.; Warren, George F. (George Frederick), 1874-1938.; Whetzel, Herbert Hice, 1877-1944.; Wiegand, Karl M. (Karl McCay), 1873-1942.; Wilder, Burt Green, 1841-1925.; Windahl, Ethan.,; Wing, H. H. (Henry Hiram), 1859-1936.; Works, George A. (George Alan), 1877-1957.; Worthen, Edmund L., 1882-1965.; Wright, Archie.; Young, Owen D., 1874-1962.; American Farm Bureau Federation.; Cooperative Grange League Federation Exchange.; Cornell University -- Students.; Cornell University -- Faculty.; Cornell University -- History.; Dairy Farmers of America.; Dairy Record Club.; Dairymen's League Cooperative Association.; Empire Livestock Marketing Cooperative.; Federal Land Bank, Springfield, Mass.; Holstein-Friesian Association of America.; Joseph Harris Company.; National Poultry Planning Committee.; New York State College of Agriculture -- Students.; New York State College of Agriculture -- Faculty.; New York State College of Agriculture. Extension Service.; New York State Conference Board of Farm Organizations.; New York State Farm Bureau Federation.; New York State Fruit Testing Cooperative Association.; New York State Grange.; New York State Horticultural Society.; New York State Poultry Council.; Northeastern Poultry Products Council.; Poultry and Egg National Board.; Producers Cooperative Commission Association of Buffalo.; Rochester Production Credit Association.; Rockefeller Foundation.; Rural Radio Network.; State University of New York College of Agriculture and Technology at Cobleskill.; United States. Department of Agriculture. Bureau of Agricultural Economics.; United States. Department of Agriculture. Office of Farm Management.; United States. Soil Conservation Service.; University of the Philippines.; Western New York Apple Growers Association.
Subjects:
Agriculture -- New York (State); Beef -- Marketing.; Poultry -- Marketing.; Dairy industry -- New York (State); Milk trade -- New York (State); Apples -- Marketing.; Farm management.; Fruit -- Cooperative marketing.; Agriculture, Cooperative -- New York (State); County agricultural agents.; Tuberculosis in cattle -- Control.; Brucellosis -- Control.; Agriculture -- Study and teaching.; Agricultural economics.; Agricultural engineering.; Agronomy.; Botany.; Conservation of natural resources.; Farmers -- New York (State); Pomology.; Vegetables -- New York (State); Seeds.
Places:
New York (State) -- Politics and government.; New York (State) -- Economic conditions.
Form and Genre Terms:
Oral histories.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. First Alphabetical Sequence (with descriptions)
Series II. Second Alphabetical Sequence (without descriptions)
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. First Alphabetical Sequence (with descriptions)
  Many of the transcripts contain information from more than one interview session, in those cases we refer to the date of the first interview.
  - Bailey, Ethel Zoe, 1889-1983, June 27, 1963; Transcript #49 (Box 2)
    Cornell Class: Spring Agriculture 1912
    Occupation: Botanist
    Interviewer: Colman
    Description: Activities of campus children at Cornell in the 1890s; relationships of L. H. Bailey to his students and colleagues; Bailey’s methods of work, attitudes and values.
  - Barrett, William, 1888-1978, February 3, 1964; Transcript #81 (Box 3)
    Cornell Class: 1915
    Occupation: Farm Manager
    Description: Farm and school experiences in Geneseo, NY; education at Cornell; work on Cornell University farms as a laborer and manager; care of experimental areas; impressions of faculty members; instruction of students in farm practices; the college boarding house; testing new equipment.
  - Bender, Ray, 1905-1975, February 21, 1964; Transcript #54 (Box 2)
    Cornell Class: 1926, MS 1928
    Occupation: County agent
    Description: Experiences as student at Cornell and as assistant county agent in Orange County and county agent in Essex County, NY; relationship to Cornell staff, to other agents, and to agricultural organizations in the county; development of birdsfoot trefoil production in Champlain Valley; farmers’ reactions to TB and brucellosis control programs; relations of Extension Service to other farm organizations; changes in the work of Extension Service.
    See also collection # 37-5-3758
  - Beneway, Frank W., 1884-1994, June 19, 1964; Transcript #105 (Box 3)
    Cornell Class: Spring Agriculture 1914
    Occupation: Farmer
    Description: Farm practices, Dutchess County, NY, ca. 1900; orchard management practices, Ontario County, NY, 1914-1964; comments on fruit marketing including effect of chain stores, organization of Western New York Apple Growers Association, Farm Bureau; Farm Credit, Rochester Production Credit Association; management of migrant labor; use of cost accounts; enlargement of farm; 4-H work, impressions of George F. Warren, Carl Ladd.
  - Benjamin, Earl Whitney, 1889-1972, July 29, 1963; Transcript #36 (Box 2)
    Cornell Class: 1911, MS 1912, PhD 1914
    Occupation: Businessman
    Description: Student experiences at Cornell; development of course and textbook in poultry marketing; the marketing of Pacific Coast eggs in New York City in the 1920s and 1930s; impressions of James E. Rice.
  - Bradfield, Richard, 1896-1981, August 13, 1962; Transcript #135 (Box 5)
    Occupation: Agronomy professor
    Description: The development of the Rockefeller Foundation programs for crop improvement in Mexico, Columbia, and the Far East, 1940-1962.
    See also collection # 21-1-2716
  - Bradley, J. Chester (James Chester), 1884-1975, December 18, 1962; Transcript #107 (Box 3)
    Cornell Class: 1906, PhD 1910
    Occupation: Entomology professor
    Description: Experiences as a student and as a professor of entomology at Cornell; recollections concerning J. H. Comstock, L.H. Bailey, M.V. Slingerland, A. D. McGilvary, W. A. Riley, James Needham; trip to South America.
    See also collection # 21-23-1717
  - Bull, Bartow W., 1874-1965, December 15, 1964; Transcript #145 (Box 5)
    Interviewer: Bliss
    Description: Activities of the Bull family in Orange County, NY agriculture, 1890-1920, especially organizing Dairymen’s League, 1907, activities in the 1916 milk strike; ditching, tiling, haying practices; early silos; use of oxen; impressions of early county agents.
  - Carey, Daniel, 1897-1976, November 24, 1964; Transcript #336 (Box 9)
    Cornell Class: 1918
    Occupation: Farm organization official
    Description: Experiences as student at Cornell; operation of dairy farm in Tompkins County, NY, 1920-1945; election as town supervisor; establishment of Tompkins County Hospital; election as director, Eastern Milk Producers Federation; experiences as assistant to Secretary of Agriculture Brannan, 1948-1950, especially liaison work with state departments of agriculture; impressions of H. H. Wing and George F. Warren.
  - Chandler, William H., 1878-1970, Undated; Transcript #124 (Box 4)
    Occupation: Pomology Professor (University of California)
    Interviewer: Dixon"
    Description: Childhood on farm in Missouri; early education and teaching experiences; further education and teaching at University of Missouri, 1901-13; difficulties of farming; quality of early agricultural studies; appointment to faculty of Cornell University, 1913; influence of Liberty Hyde Bailey, professor at Cornell; tenure as head of department; study of pomology established at Cornell; relationship between Cornell and State Agricultural Experiment Station at Geneva, New York; interaction between farmers and university study of agriculture; decision to accept position at University of California, Southern Branch, 1923; work with California agriculture; importance of soil chemistry; Martin R. Huberty; John Eliot Coit; Vernon T. Stoutemeyer; Claude B. Hutchison; start of floriculture program at UCLA; contributions of plant pathologists; fruit growers' problems; B. H. Crocheron; Ralph E. Smith; Thomas F. Hunt; E. W. Hilgard.
  - Cowles, G. Harold, 1902-1980, December 10, 1964; Transcript #121 (Box 4)
    Cornell Class: Spring Agriculture 1927
    Interviewer: Windahl
    Description: Experiences framing in Chautauqua County, NY, 1910-1965, especially acquisition of equipment, fertilization practices, feeding practices, haymaking, development of purebred Holstein herd, work with Holstein-Friesian Association and with Soil Conservation Service, labor procurement and management, drainage, milk marketing, sugar bush operations; experiences as student at Cornell; satisfactions and stresses of dairy farming.
  - Eames, Arthur J., 1881-1969, December 6, 1962; Transcript #24 (Box 1)
    Occupation: Botany professor
    Description: Descriptions of the staff and activities of the Dept. of Botany in Sage college and in the College of Agriculture at Cornell; relationships to other departments; field trips; recollections concerning G. F. Atkinson, W. W. Rowlee, H. H. Whetzel, K. M. and Mrs. Wiegand.
    See also collection # 21-1-3354
  - Fogg, Verne A., 1897-1987, May 9, 1963; Transcript #117 (Box 4)
    Description: Childhood experiences in Vermont; student activities at Massachusetts Agricultural College; county agent work in Windsor County, VT and Chenango County, NY; the Pharsalia project. TB eradication; development of retail services of GLF; GLF research in electric fencing, farm freezing, rubber tired farm equipment, pain, other areas; GLF marketing activities; Crown Point lumber mill; decision to abandon GLF income tax exempt status, GLF credit policies; formation of GLF insurance company; development of GLF petroleum distribution; management of Texas City Refining Company; reminiscences concerning G. F. Warren, H. E. Babcock, Cornell extension specialists.
    See also collection # 3068
  - Foster, Edward Shields, 1901-1973, Undated; Transcript #146 (Box 5)
    Cornell Class: 1925
    Description: Childhood experiences; student activities at Cornell; county agent work in Chautauqua and Suffolk Counties; Long Island agriculture in the 1920s; work as executive secretary of New York Farm Bureau Federation; Farm Bureau policymaking; relationships with American Farm Bureau Federation; political activities of organized agriculture in New York; Irwin roads law; rural electrification; separation of Farm Bureau and Extension Service in NY; development of “new model” Farm Bureau organization; poultry disease laboratories; brucellosis eradication; relationship of NYFB to commodity groups and other farm organizations; expansion of NYFB staff; development of marketing program; work with educational organizations; comments concerning New York State School Boards Association; impressions of H. E. Babcock, George F. Warren, Archie Wright, Earl Smith, Ed O’Neal, E. R. Eastman, Joe Barnum, Frank Gannett.
    See also collection # 3690
  - Genung, Albert Benjamin, 1890-1963, November 23, 1962; Transcript #18 (Box 1)
    Cornell Class: 1913
    Occupation: Agricultural Economics professor
    Description: Student experiences at Cornell; evaluation of faculty members, especially George F. Warren; work in Bureau of Agricultural Economics, USDA; reminiscences concerning H. C. Taylor, H. C. Wallace; Warren and the price of gold; evaluation of Warren’s influence in agricultural economics.
  - Green, Donald, 1903-1989, December 3, 1964; Transcript #133 (Box 5)
    Description: Experiences in blast furnace operation in northern New York and Massachusetts, 1923-1932; the management of Chazy Orchards, Chazy, NY, 1940-1965, especially drainage, spraying, fertilization, planting, labor procurement and management, credit, cost accounting, sources of information, relations with Farm Bureau and Extension Service; experiences as president of New York State Farm Bureau, 1959-1961, especially representing Farm Bureau in Albany; observations concerning New York State Horticultural Society, insurance services available to farmers in NY; recollections concerning Fred Porter and Edward S. Foster.
  - Hart, Van Breed, 1894-1976, September 13, 1962; Transcript #4 (Box 1)
    Description: Description of George F. Warren as teacher, researcher, and head of the Dept. of Agricultural Economics at Cornell; 1912-1938.
  - Hawley, Warren Waldo, Jr., 1891-1982, January 23, 1963; Transcript #38 (Box 2)
    Cornell Class: Spring Agriculture 1911
    Description: Childhood experiences; student experiences at Cornell; impressions of George F. Warren; farm experiences in Genesee County; development of cost account work in the county; Farm Bureau activities in New York State; relationships of the New York to the American Farm Bureau Federation; separation of Farm Bureau and Extension Service in NY; availability of farm credit and development of Production Credit; Producers’ Cooperative Commission Association of Buffalo; poultry certification; service on USDA Commodity Credit Advisory Committee.
  - Herrick, Glenn Washington, 1870-1965, June 20, 1963; Transcript #26 (Box 1)
    Cornell Class: 1896
    Description: Reflections concerning I. P. Roberts, J. H. Comstock, L. H. Bailey; reaction of faculty of New York State College of Agriculture to Bailey’s resignation as dean.
    See also collection # 21-23-844
  - Huttar, John C., 1902-1988, November 24, 1964; Transcript #123 (Box 4)